Is it okay if I start? I mean, no.
Yes. Okay. So um I would like to explain my
Okay. So um I would like to explain my
situation um
list life as you call it. Uh it's um
there are there are several commitments
that I have right so I have my job
commitments I have my family commitments
um I have all the extra work that I do I
do some research on top of that and
there are some various hobbies that I
would like to continue doing and um
various other engagements
um everything's a lot of things that I'm
committed to actually
um and um the way I see what what helps
me in terms of the um hindrances
right the five hindrances. So for
example to avoid uh slot and torper I do
have a lot of energy uh and I invested
in various fields not just da but
various fields and um for example to um
to especially to to uh avoid remorse
right restlessness restlessness and
remorse I tend to arrange my u or manage
my time in very tight
time slots. So I would do I don't know I
would do two hours of writing articles,
two hours of preparing for this, one
hour of this. So I have my my day is
pretty um well organized I would say.
Mhm. So these are the two things that I kind
So these are the two things that I kind
of have problem with restlessness and
remorse because I have so many things
and this is what helps really arranging
things neatly and uh then sticking to
the schedule however you know to to the
greatest extent possible if something
comes up then I don't feel um remorseful
about it or regretting that I had did
not do certain things because I did my
best actually I think that
um but uh Then I would also like to
arrange my dharma practice you know in a
time slot in a tight maybe I mean there
are certain things that I you develop
that you practice throughout the day
regardless of what I'm doing I will um
you know I will develop mindfulness
and uh discernment of various mental
states that I'm in um so I do that
constantly I don't need a separate time
slot for that but at the same time I
feel this urgency that you know I need
to develop this field as well I not as
well but primarily so this is the most
important thing that I'm doing my my
most my primary um goal or aspiration is
dharma and development of of this um
awareness um enlightenment factors I was just uh
um enlightenment factors I was just uh
yeah briefly today I was looking at
these again. Um, so I don't have for
example the problems with the
So what's what's stopping you? question
is so the what's so the mindful so I
would like you to actually I was hoping
that you could give me like some
structured advice on how to how to
practice let's say how to set aside a
certain amount of time each day and do
concentrated practice for the things
that I need to uh develop maybe I I
don't know um how do you what would you
say what should I do exactly in that
let's say I don't know does Does it help
to have half an hour set aside in the
morning and half an hour in the evening?
And what exactly should I be doing in
that half or or one hour a day? I was
hoping you could give me some guidelines
on how to do it in a structured way to
very targeted.
Right. Well, if you do want something to
structure, uh, make it like a sa study obviously
uh, make it like a sa study obviously
[clears throat]
because the knowledge is what stays with
you even when you're busy or occupied or
overwhelmed by other things, not not
your meditation technique. So
understanding will stay with you
throughout the day of that, you know,
the clarity you you you gained on
account of pondering on things and
reading the sutras and so on.
But another question I do have to sort
of get back to is uh you say remorse,
restlessness and remorse is a hindrance.
So you structure your day so you don't
experience it. Uh why would you be
remorseful? Are you doing something
immoral? Oh no no no. I'm uh you know
Oh no no no. I'm uh you know
exactly exact exactly. So so what what
is the remorse there for? if you're not
doing anything bad.
Well, that you haven't accomplished
everything that you're supposed to have
because that kind of affects the whole
department then. And uh we're looking at
uh publications and uh uh you know how
but why why why didn't you accomplish
everything you had? Is it because you
didn't try hard enough or could simply
there was physically not possible?
Oh, poor time management. So that's what
what I'm working now,
right? poor time management which is kind of
poor time management which is kind of
part of work. So you kind of work and
learn and get better. Yeah. So in other
words, your remorse is not very
rational. There is no rational basis like lack of
There is no rational basis like lack of
virtue, unh wholesome behavior,
intentional mistake to be remorseful
for. Yet you're remorseful.
But slacking off. I mean like um
but are you are you sliding off or are
you just can't keep up with that level?
Which one is it?
Sometimes you know it's just
to me sounds like like you're not you
you probably have too much which is why
you can't do everything.
Yes. So thinking that you must uh manage that
So thinking that you must uh manage that
remorse by further distraction is going
to make your remorse even worse
because everything now becomes a
distraction from remorse.
And if you don't keep the level of
engagement that you that you're sort of
occupied with, remorse comes back. In
other words, you're trying to outrun it,
but you run out of energy. You have to
and then it catches up with you.
Yes. And then I and then I collapse.
So that's the problem. And now another
problem is that on top of that, you want
to add the dharma practice as another
occupation during the day to keep you on
top of the remorse.
Yes. and and that's that's not going to
happen. Especially if you start reading the
Especially if you start reading the
sutras and structuring the way I said
you'll be more aware of your remorse
even there is nothing remorseful that
you did. So that's why the hindrances
yes if there is a factual basis for
remorse guilt as in you know unh
wholesome behavior you know that's the
bit where where you confess you
acknowledge the mistake and so on but
the rest you have to endure it that's
the point on the hindrances they are
irrational um so you mustn't take them at the face
um so you mustn't take them at the face
value as oh no this remorse is is is
fine yes I am guilty and I must deal
with it no you must actually just uh
endure it as such and not try to outrun
it either. That's why hindrances they
don't really care about anything else
except uh to move you. That's their only
concern. They want you to make you act
on account of them. Whether it's
restlessness, remorse, sensual desire,
ill will, doubt, sloth, they want you to
act out of it. That's that's it. The
goal is accomplished when you do. So you
don't overcome hindrances by structuring
your day so you don't become aware of
them. You overcome them by not acting
out of them throughout your day.
Not acting out on feeling this.
So the remorse arises and you just have
to endure it. Well, first you can re
revise your mind and check have I done
anything unh wholesome by body speech or
mind intention or otherwise? No. Remorse
is still there. Okay, that's the
practice now. So you want to to
incorporate the the the dharma part in
your busy day. That's the dharma part.
Endure the remorse on account of
basically not being able to keep up with
the projected sense of duty and
everything else.
Yeah. And that's it. See
And that's it. See
in one of your talks you said how
important it was to feel um to feel
contentment content like this internal contentment
content like this internal contentment
that is not based on anything external
just this general feeling of all right
this is how I understood it.
Yeah it is.
and didn't mention something that I
thought was very much connected with
what we were just discussing.
I don't remember what you said. It's so
hard to be content with yourself with
when there are so many obligations that
are, you know, piling up and you can't
keep up and you haven't done everything
that you should have done and there are
just new things coming in all the time.
She's also she also has a very stressful
job. I would just would you like to say
something about and also very stressful
job and a lot of things I want to do in
in my spare time. Um but I keep running
out of time.
Um and I but I'm not uh as structured as
she is. Um I I get less things done in
one day than she does. Uh so time
management is a big problem for me.
Yeah. Well, it's it's it's all relative.
like the amount of things you do in a
day. It's again what what's the measure
for that? Who's the measure? What's the
criteria? Because you might be able to
you might end up doing everything and
the mind still wants to do more or the
mind will still find to do more. So the
contentment won't come from you
structuring your day perfectly or
meeting every deadline in time. It will
basically come from you being able to
draw a line for yourself.
So being able to keep your mind from
sort of overspilling and becoming
irrational on account of duty and
everything else that's where the
contentment become and that takes
development internally.
So in a way I'm saying basically uh
being able to say no to yourself to some
extent to your own mind
to your own mind
uh because deep down you already know
that you know you're doing like well
enough but yes the mind can always focus
on the lack not enough could be better
could be this and that becomes a habit
because you keep letting it uh focus on
that and then that becomes your your
your pretty much your your viewpoint.
point always always finding fault in in
your own or or or basically always
regarding your own actions and results
and behavior as not enough not enough
not enough. And that's a mental habit.
That's not a factual state of things.
What's enough is completely relative?
How do you change that?
Well, by what you didn't do and start
focusing on what you did do or
Yeah. Well, they you already know what
you did. So you change that by uh
choosing to attend to that side of
things. And when the mind pressures you
to think about things you didn't do and
all the you know irrational sense of
guilt that's what you have to endure
that discomfort. But see because people
don't want to endure any form of
discomfort. They give in to the mind
thinking about these doubtful matters
and so on hoping it will reach the
resolution so it will free them from the
discomfort. But practically speaking,
they just feed the animal further and
that creates in further discomfort down
the line.
So instead of um waiting for the
discomfort to pile up, you have an
option basically to endure that
discomfort in a form of a mind that's
being said no to.
But if you don't want to endure that,
then you pay the price later with more
discomfort when the mind is fully
overwhelmed by the hindrances and doubt
and guilt and so on and fault finding.
You make this into a kind of meditation.
So you
I was just going to say that is actually
exactly what samadei is. Yeah.
Keeping your mind in check, composing
it, not letting it spill out and and
take you with it.
So in terms of these enlightenment
factors right so you have the
mindfulness you have the discrimination
of mental state you see that this is
happening you you are you are clear
about what's going on and then you apply
concentration um in terms of enduring
um in terms of enduring
um
focusing on the body
is that what you would suggest suggest
doing? No, I'd suggest what I just suggested.
No, I'd suggest what I just suggested.
Um, so
if it gets too much, yes, set aside set
set some time aside per per day. Uh, and
don't use it to sort of ignore or escape
things, but use it just to compose your
mind on what's right there.
And that is what's right there is the
pressure of duty that you're not doing
while you're meditating. So you don't
want to be you don't want to be trying
to escape that. You want to be
containing it and that's that's your
practice. So you start doing it in that
measured sense in a controlled
environment. But the more you do it like
that the more you'll be able to do it in
less controlled environment. Obviously
now you can't just overnight having you
know having had a busy life overwhelmed
from all angles and and responsibilities
and duties you can't just overnight stop
your mind from moving. But you can
certainly make a make a gradual training
of it. But again, the point is to
recognize your situation and train in
regard to it, not train at the expense
of it. And by that I mean, okay, so I'll
compose my mind and practice so I don't
have to deal with these things. One way
or the other, something would be
pressuring your mind. One way or the
other, something will be trying to pull
it. One way or the other, hindrances are
there unless you're in another hand. So
one way or the other, same thing needs
to be dealt with by everyone.
That's your mind moving on account of
basically hindrances and emotions
and then you get you become more
resilient to such states right yeah you
yeah actually I have something that is
connected because it's all goes into
these um seven enlightenment factors so
mindfulness discrimination of u
discernment of mental state
and then energy
um and concentration. But then there are
three which I hope I was hoping you
could help me or help us develop the the
the rapture tranquility and equinimity.
So how how do you do that? I mean how do
you do you evoke those feelings of
rapture? Well, you don't you don't really they're
Well, you don't you don't really they're
the result of developing the previous
factors. So when your mindfulness is developed
So when your mindfulness is developed
you obviously well within your
mindfulness when you contemplate things
you do so in a clearer manner. So that's
how you're developing that investigation
of factors how it's translated. You
can't be investigating certain topic
trying to come to the bottom of the
meaning and understand it if you're not
mindful of it.
So it's not 1 2 3 4 5 6 7. They're
basically developed one through the
other. So you will get energy for example you
So you will get energy for example you
know to practice or or whatever when you
know what the practice is.
So it's it's easy to to to sort of
become inspired to do something when
know exactly what you need to do and
what the result will be.
So the investigation of factors can
clarify that for you. Then the goal
becomes clearer. Then the energy arises
on its own
because now you know what you need to do
and same joy on account of it arises on
its own and then the tranquility because
you're already removed from unh
wholesome states practicing in the right
direction will follow and equinimity is
the result of it you don't evoke
equinimity that's basically when you
complete everything else you are
economous
yeah it's strange how when I spend time
uh in in a in a monastery for example
with with you guys um then for a while
after and during that time I feel this
probably is what I would say rapture and
tranquility is like an underlying it's
like one tone underlying tone to
everything else that's happening it
feels like being protected somehow
against you know letting your mind run
wild with these various it's like being
I don't know in a sort of a balanced
lovely feeling of uh
I don't know in tranquility probably and
yeah so and then it runs out
then I run out of this fuel and then I
have to keep coming but I I don't know I
was I was hope yeah I thought this was
um it's pro it's not connected to it's
probably that I really am removed from
everything else and I focus on what I
think is my top priority in life and I
spend time with people who's also top
whose top priority is also the same
thing um in the monastic community and
then this gives me well great joy really
but then it wears out when I'm in you
know daily life
yeah after
well that's the thing you have to see
basically that it's not it's not the
enlightenment factor that comes from you
because that would not wear out
it might be resembling the idea of it
but the fact is it depends on the
circumstances that when when those
change it it it runs out it cannot stay.
Yeah. So it's not like to to say oh you must
So it's not like to to say oh you must
never experience that or something.
There's nothing wrong with it but you
should certainly not conflate it because
sometimes people think okay see when I
was in the monastery this joy was great
everything felt effortless energy was
there because everybody was doing the
same thing. It was so inspiring. So all
I need to do is place this physical body
in the monastery and the work will be
done for me by that inspiration. That
doesn't even that will run out. That
will happens to people as well. They
come and they think that being in the
monastery will sort of makes every makes
the practice you know persist on a
certain level all the time and it
doesn't. When the honeymoon period is
over you're back onto you know what
you've been carrying internally before
you came to the monastery and you
realize okay that's what you need to
deal with like whether you're outside or
inside doesn't matter. So you can use
that inspiration that that joy that you
get to inspire you to develop it on your
own but not to inspire you to project it
even more onto the external
circumstances and just try to manage
those. Wonderful. Thank you. I think I got
Wonderful. Thank you. I think I got
exactly what I was hoping to get the
answer. How to do it and what to do. So
wonderful. There you go.
There you go.
I may [clears throat] just u add a
little bit something to this discussion
and uh I fear that I might sound perhaps
as a broken record.
I think something that I've mentioned
already I think at least twice. We find
ourselves in a similar setting. We're
both embedded in the academic framework
and uh we're both very much uh
interested in pursuing the dharma
and uh it's just um
this is not necessarily a question more
of a commentary but I do feel this uh
that there is this um need or craving
a very problematic word in this
particular millu
uh but maybe potentially a noble craving
uh for enhancing the the the dharma
practice um in in some sort of a inter
intermediary or
interim state or phase or something.
state or phase or something.
So how would how would you do how would
you do that? What are your ideas?
My ideas okay so I I was I have been
thinking about this quite a lot. So um
the um the opasa uh meetings or the
opasa setting I found extremely useful
and valuable. uh so the fact that you
have at least once per month a meeting
of this sort either online or even
preferably in person but also I don't
know the the ability maybe of u
I don't know how this would be carried
out but uh the the to intensify somehow
the the lay involvement in the monastic
community and I think that I I'm
becoming more and more um aware of Why
having uh
you know the why the presence of the
monastics in the city or in the near
vicinity could be immensely beneficial
for this particular purpose because you
can have something that's present uh
there for your I mean on a more regular
basis and can serve as some sort of a
intermediary between what you do uh in
the context of the city and your job And
then when you are able to go to the
monastery and maybe be there
but I don't know I was thinking of you
know this group maybe finding ways to
do the suta studies together or I don't
know com joint sittings uh the again the
the different possibilities of doing
something at the monastery for a for a
weekend or something like that. It could
be maybe structured in in in
[clears throat] the groups of three
[snorts] to five people. I I don't know.
But uh having more access to say the
dharma talks and dhamma discussions of
this type uh uh the suta readings uh the
joint practice. I don't know. Um several
different options. I have no good ideas.
I'm just uh I feel that this is an
ongoing thing that is going through my
mind and I'm thinking
well all that all that is I mean fairly
possible. The monastery is here, monks
are here. So, it's just a question of
you finding time and organizing
yourselves to come and meditate or or
stay as guests and and partake. There's
nothing really extraordinary there
except trying to slot it in your busy
schedule, which is basically why you
want to do this in the first place
because there's too much of other things
happening. So,
Precisely. [snorts and laughter]
This is the the reason why I said that I
would probably sound like like a broker
record and you will give me the same
advice. [laughter]
Uh I'm I'm aware of this. I'm aware of
this completely. Just uh wanted to maybe
point this out so that maybe Martina and
Mariana and possibly Freya and Alo also
start wi with a bit of a brainstorming.
Right. Right.
Yeah. Well, that's the thing like like
the whole group, how many of you are?
Yeah. You can certainly either something
yourselves that would revolve around
dharmas study uh or you know involving
the monastery one way or the other but
um yeah it's not really it doesn't sound
like something that's impossible to do.
Um
yeah I think we should definitely do
this. uh we there are a few of there's a
few of us who read the sutas and doesn't
have to be about the sutas necessarily
but at least it gives you some sort of
framework we say okay let's focus on the
today it was going to um probably
trigger all sorts of questions about
various topics from our own lives anyway
I think it would be wonderful if uh we
could do that would you be able to would
you be willing uh so I'm asking
venerables uh and would you be willing
to to come and um and sit in listen in
and help us out when we get lost there a
bit with
come come where
to to these meetings I mean if they're
online because they're probably they
would probably have to be online now
right it would be if we if we had such
weekly meetings maybe or
um
well I I don't really know I and when
I'm available I can do it but I cannot
certainly commit to it before even
knowing how frequently it happens. Uh
but that's the thing you don't want to I
mean if you if you have somebody extra
join in that's great but don't start
planning when you haven't even done it
with too many requirements. Make it as
simple as possible something that
everybody can do. Not like oh well now
the monk's the monk's busy so we can't
do it. No that that should not make a
difference. If you all find time,
If you all find time,
get together and do it. And if there is
a monk available, great. If not, well,
you still have something to do.
Uh, but if you involve too many moving
parts before you even start, it probably
not going to hold.
The first question, a very simple one is
and uh the reason why I'm asking it is
because uh um I've now read the
Dhamapada uh and am well into Majima
Nikayas and I'm occasionally reading
trying to read other uh uh nikayas as
well. But I was just curious whether you
would have any suggestion as to you know
how one might approach this um
more systematically or would you have
any suggestions as to how one might
proceed with this uh endeavor in
general. What I mean by this is you know
when I plunged into the nikayas you just
go okay you read one sutas you read one
suta and then you move to the other and
so on and so forth and eventually I went
I had to go back and started start doing
uh like these comprehensive notes
because you have so many cross cross
references and you just tend to forget
many of the things and um you know um a
certain key or a suggestion
as to how one might go about doing this
so that it would
well again the sole purpose of it is to
to understand the meaning of it. So if
um having a systematic approach aids
that that's fine but don't sort of uh
lose perspective and become sort of too
concerned with how to most efficiently
and systematically approach this to you
know to the to the letter. They will
basically make you forget that you're
there for the meaning and the work that
you put in won't go to waste for as long
as you're trying to understand the
sutras. Doesn't matter if you read from
the middle or from the back or from the
beginning. But if you if you yourself find some
But if you if you yourself find some
sort of like what you just said sounds
to me already like some system you have.
You started reading then you started
writing the notes down then you go back
to it then you read again then you
compare the notes then maybe you write
some more notes. U there's nothing wrong
with that. So basically whatever system
you have should be guided by that um
effort to understand the meaning of the
sutas not like hey I want to implement
this system because it sounds
intellectually pleasing to me that it
might work but I'm not actually doing it
from the point of view of the meaning is
the first that's where my effort is
rooted. So you could just I mean for somebody it
So you could just I mean for somebody it
might be already quite systematic to say
just read the sutas from the beginning
till the end.
That's it. That's already a form of a
system. U but I think as I said what
you're doing sounds perfectly fine. Take
anaya read it write down the notes and
you'll see like some sutas will stand
for you more than the other sutras. And
that's when you, you know, you go back
to them, compare the notes, find
different translations, kind of go
deeper into Pali maybe to see if there's
something you're missing, some nuances.
Uh, and keep doing that and keep
repeating that.
Yeah. Okay. Thank you. I I guess what I
was maybe um looking for is after a
while you see that there are sutas that
are quite similar in many ways
and that there are certain of course
parts and chunks of sutas that repeat in
different sutas. Uh so this is something
that I was thinking of maybe you know
whether there's they're
possibly useful and I'm guessing there
are uh either traditional or
maybe even scholarly ways of grouping
sutas so that for instance when you read
one you read two or three additional
sutas that are similar
that that cover a sim cover similar
ground or something like that so that
it's more
I don't know it's more it's more focused
or more um
thematically congruous in a certain
sense maybe this is something that I was
maybe this is something that I was
thinking of or yeah because right now
I'm doing what you basically described
so trying to read the sutas trying to
understand them jot down the structures
the main notions and then figure out
these uh
um parallels myself. Yes, I I I've been
using occasionally the suta central, but
still you know you you have so many ways
as to how you can approach this. So I
was just curious whether bonte had some
no not specifically no just uh yeah any
tools you can get table they would but
again uh it all comes down to if you
understand any suta fully you know
relevant suta you'll be at least a sort
of balance. So it's not a question of
thematically collecting the most sutas
that increases your chance or something.
Um it's basically how you attend them
and uh and you know how much of your
current views are obstructing your
understanding. That's what the issue is.
See if you just keep drilling through
reading the sutras either thematically
or individually it doesn't matter.
That's what that's that's what counts
that that repetitive effort. Um but see
what you're suggesting now it's great if
somebody were to do it but it often
becomes a distraction for people in a
sense wow it would be great if somebody
thematically orders a sutas so let me
spend six months now thematically
ordering the sutas and people do that
and they think I am still see I'm still
working with the sutas I'm still getting
no you're not no you're absolutely just
externally collecting these things
without opening to look what's inside
and that's what when when scholar
scholarly attitude takes over
uh and and that's the danger of it. So
if you thematic end up arranging
thematically through your own actual
individual attempts to understand that's
fine but don't don't assume it as some
sort of an external occupation project
that's worthwhile doing. I mean sure it
might make you some merit if somebody
else comes and reads those sutas and
gets the right view on account of it but
I'm pretty sure that's not why you would
be doing it.
Yeah. Okay, thank you. I I would have a
perhaps even more specific or concrete
concrete question. It's it's a
hermeneutic question of sorts. Uh and it
comes often in in the sutas and I was
just wondering how you would suggest one
goes about understanding this. So let me
give you an example. There are certain
circularities within the
sutas uh which which one finds
uh which which one finds
well they are one would one could say
logically problematic uh and they don't
really get uh called out in the sutas um
so for instance um in the right view
sutna um
where you have these uh uh different uh
explanations of what is right view.
There are several different categories
and the first category for instance is
uh understanding unh wholesome and the
root of unh wholesome and then wholesome
and the root of unh wholesome and then
um when Satiputa I think that he he's
the main protagonist in this uh suta uh
explains what onho is he says killing of
living beings taking what is not given
and so on and so forth and he ends with
and wrong view
and then When he says what is wholesome,
he says not killing living beings, not
taking what is not giving and the right
view. So the problem here is obvious. So
you want to know what the right view is
and the answer is you have to understand
the wholesome and the unh wholesome. And
when you define the wholesome and the
unh wholesome, you define it by
mentioning the right view and the wrong
view. So you have to have the right view
in order to be able to understand the
right view which is a a a clear example
of circularity which is of course
problematic and there are several this
is just one example.
So well that example for example that's
it's not quite what you say because it's
not that he only says that it's not that
he says the right view is the wholesome
is the right view and the right view is
the wholesome and full stop. He gives
you a whole list of things that are also
unh wholesome.
So there's plenty of you to do and if
you do that then you get to see that the
remaining bit even when you were doing
everything else that was wholesome was
your wrong view.
In other words, it's a vicious circle in
the same sense that you know a heroine
addict will cease to be an addict if he
stops taking heroin because of which
he's an addict which is why he keeps
taking the heroine which is why he's an
addict. All he needs to do is stop doing
that vicious circle. not just a question
of of finding like a logical basis for
it. is to see that everything else that
S puts are listed there are things to be
done and understood
and that in itself will undo that last
thing which is to be done and understood
the wrong view because of which you have
the wrong view
or when people say well the Buddha said
desire is bad but isn't the desire for
aranchip also bad so thus I shouldn't
desire well he didn't quite say desire
is bad in itself regardless of where you
aim it
so desire the perpet Petous desire is
bad. Desire that can end in sessation of
desire is good. As I gave the example, I
don't know if it was in the recording or
in person with somebody, you know,
desire to become healthy while you're
ill is still your illman's desire.
But it's actually desire that can make
you seek out and find a doctor. It will
make you follow the certain diet. It
will make you take the medicine. It will
result then in your curing, complete
curation and freedom from desire. So
desire did end the desire and that's not
a contradiction.
Okay, I I I see that uh I think I
understand this point. Um
but there are many examples where you
would have a certain notion that is say
conditioned by something else. For
instance, you might say content contact
is I'm not sure whether this is the the
appropriate sequence, but you might say
that contact is conditioned by matter
and form. And then when you describe
what constitutes
u uh form, you will mention for instance
contact or something like that. So you
might have a it's it's in the same suta.
So you have a certain phenomenon which
is conditioned by something else and
then when you [clears throat] unpack
this what's conditioning this it's
basically the same.
Yeah. Yeah. Cuz things are not linear. It's
Yeah. Cuz things are not linear. It's
not 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 10 11 12.
It's basically all as it was described
in Namarupa determines vinana in the
same and vinana determines namarupa.
So how's that possible? Logically that's
impossible. Either one thing depends on
the other or the other depends on this
one. But you can't say well this depends
on the other. When you look at that one
it depends on the other one.
So consciousness determines names name
and form and name and form determines
consciousness. How's that possible? Well
you understand that you understood the
principle of
means you got the right view.
And what's the principle is with this
this is
so two simultaneously present things at
the same time but not on the same level.
The problem of logical circularities
when you assume they're on the same
level and then it doesn't make sense but
they're not on the same level. That's
why dharma precedes the logic.
That doesn't mean dharma is illogical.
That which is illogical is that which
denies the logic. Dharma doesn't deny
the logic. It just precedes it even
deeper structurally.
Is it a bit like moving from 2D into 3D?
Sorry. Yeah. Supposedly, but even that, see,
Yeah. Supposedly, but even that, see,
you are now the observer of the 3D. This
is even harder because moving from 2D,
you are the 3D. So, you can't step
outside and see yourself looking at the
2D. No, not like that. Yeah,
I know. I know. But I'm just saying even
that example can be taken in a linear
way on the same level.
2D, 3D, it doesn't matter. The point is
you have to involve that other part of
your being which is usually well which
is that which attends to the logic.
But you mustn't dismiss the logic
either. See, sometimes people understood
this and then they go too much the other
way and dismiss the reason. And the
Buddha never did that.
And you shouldn't be doing that because
you dismiss the reason you will
basically shooting you will be shooting
yourself in the foot.
No, this is the reasonal reasonable and
and reasoning whereby you recognize your
situation. How do you find a way out
that's not involving mere reasoning
that also involves that pretty much the
emotional side of your being that can
then be cooled down and uprooted from
passion and so on without forsaking and
sacrificing reason and you get that in
other forms of Buddhism when they got
this sense but then they for they
completely dismissed the reason and
started saying nonsense pretty much just
absolute contradictions just to throw
you off the because you know too much
thinking thinking is the problem. It's
not the problem.
Ignorance is the problem. Passion is the
problem. Aversion is the problem.
Delusion is the problem.
Thinking was never the problem.
Would you say that then the the this uh
specific example that you mentioned of
the consciousness
uh conditioning the namarupa and
namarupa conditioning the consciousness.
Would you say that uh basically this is
a way of expressing the idea that say
the the dynamics of existence are
something that basically you cannot
surpass in the sense of that you will
find something more stable than this.
And once you have this dynamism, this is
basically what is the the only ground
the dynamic ground that you can
find or get as close to as possible.
Asking for something that is more
fundamental or more stable or having a
more uh unilateral ground so to speak is
almost the same as as having a coin with
two sides that is circling around and
asking yeah but which side is the which
side is the ground and it's basically a
known question because
these these aspects are
well in a way but the thing is see even
your statement now sounds a bit like a
way of of repossessing that ground on a
on an external level as a sense of
safety But just
so you want to contemplate consciousness
and now and and name and form. You don't
do that in a on a like a on a leveled
platform as you would do with logic A
and logical thing B. You do it by if you
are thinking about yourself being
conscious that is undermined by your
name and form.
If you are thinking about your name and
form that is undermined by your
consciousness at the same time. So you
can't think think two things at those
two things at the same time on the same
level. You either attend one which means
it under it's undermined by the other.
And that's the principle understanding
the other without trying to attend it
directly because then it will become
another one and something else and the
other thing would be undermining it.
Mhm. It's basically like like the figure
ground thing. You can have the figure
without the ground, but once you switch
something to become a figure, the other
thing becomes a ground. But you cannot
get away from this uh dynamic, so to
speak. No, no, no. That's impossible.
No, no, no. That's impossible.
Yeah. Okay. Okay. Thank you. [snorts]
[snorts]
Um maybe along completely different
lines, but um the feeling the some some
circularity maybe in this but maybe not
let's take a look um I think our main
issue is some sort of anxiety and panic
right anxiety panic uh we are this is
how we were brought up uh constant
achievement is what counts constantly
looking outside the feelings of
obligation guilt etc so everything kind
of feeds up into that anxiety and panic
uh now that can of course result in
wonderful achievements which mean
absolutely nothing uh once they are
either gone or once you are mentally
exhausted that means nothing then so
it's kind of the panic that we are kind
of trying to surpass trying to appease
um appease appease the mind gladden
gladden the mind I've heard this
expression in various dharma talks as
well gladden the mind like yeah sit you
know letting things cool off. Um at the
same time you can see in sutras sutras
as well um kind of the the message of
urgency uh where you have uh you know
examples such as oh how how extremely
rare it is to to be given a human birth.
how extremely rare it is and how lucky
you should consider yourself to be if
you encounter the dharma in this life
and that kind of in my case anyway feeds
into the panic the kind of the the
enlightenment panic
and do you see the connection
no it should well the thing is like
first with the gladdening of the mind
you know I I guess there are two ways
you can go about it so like I don't know
imagine you stick your hand into burning
fire and it burns and then you pour the cold
and it burns and then you pour the cold
water over your hand while it's still in
the burning fire. So, you are gladdening
your hand
from the burning embers, but you're not
letting go of the burning embers.
So, that's that's one way of gladening.
Another way of gladening is get your
hand out of the fire and don't put it
back in, and it will come down, cool
off, and be glad that it's not burning
anymore. So again it comes down to when people
So again it comes down to when people
don't really review their actions, don't
keep an eye on them, don't don't keep
themsel in check in terms of their you
know life engagements and then want to
do this glidening and janna practice
just basically as a paste over an
infected wound.
I was like that's not going to change
anything and that's certainly not what
the Buddha was teaching. So gladdening
the mind is done by pretty much removing
the mind from things that that perturb
it in a sense. So actions that are
overwhelming you that are piling up
maybe you should revise and see whether
it's all worth it to what extent it's
worth it. And as I said in the beginning
of this talk, draw a line for yourself
because otherwise it's endless.
And which then brings to the second
point is same this oh you know a rare
opportunity to be a human and hear the
dharma. Yes, but that's not the blessing
part. The blessing is if you make the
effort and understand the dharma. If you
just heard the dharma, that's it. So
what? Make no difference to whether
there's right view or not. But people
like to think that just hearing the
dharma somehow purifies them. It
doesn't. The actions, the virtue, that's what
The actions, the virtue, that's what
purifies you. The mindfulness.
Um [snorts and clears throat]
so so that's that's what you want to be
developing. So you can feel um blessed
that you are able to hear the dharma,
but I think it's it's more correct to
feel what you are feeling, which is
sense of urgency because it's not just
about hearing the dharma, it's about
practicing it. And yeah, it is a rare
opportunity to practice it. So, so
practice it. Yeah,
I know. It's just um I kind of found
myself in this now because um I you know
I'm a complete noob and beginner. I know
nothing about the the sutas and stuff.
I've never meditated and basically what
I'm looking for is a kind of tool to
manage my stress and uh and panic. So
it's not something that I can take and
and do just in those times when the
panic comes.
I guess it's something you have to do
and commit to.
Well, the closest to the closest to a
tool you would get that would really
work all the time is like start just on
a daily basis uh practicing mindfulness
of the like in terms of motivation
behind your action. Any action, not just
work, anything you want to do. Know for
yourself why you want to do it.
So force your mind to go in that like
slightly broader perspective whereby it
starts having a better um overview of
your situation.
What what you want to do now is you want
to find a tool that will like if you
engage with it, it will make the stress
go away and then you go back to it and
then when the stress builds up, you want
to, you know, which is basically you
want like you know take a pill to take
the pain away but not remove the
underlying cause for the pain.
Well, I'd like to remove that as well.
Yeah. Well, that's the thing. You can't remove
Well, that's the thing. You can't remove
that for as long as you're too occupied
with managing the symptoms.
So sometimes you have to allow the
symptoms to manifest to see how deeply
the problem goes.
But if you're too busy just treating
immediate headache, you won't know what
other symptoms follow. So you won't know
what condition you have. You might just
think you have a headache, but you might
have something much more.
So the symptoms, as I said, you would
you can manage if it's too much, but
fundamentally you want to understand
what's behind it. So the stress you're
experiencing and so on and the panic is
the result of life in general. So it's
unavoidable. That's the first thing. So
what what can you avoid and what you can
do within that is make sure your actions
are not rooted in unh wholesome. They
would then be fueling that stress even
more and taking it out of your hands.
And the only way you can know whether
your actions are rooted in you know
wholesome or unh wholesome in too much
desire in anger in ill will in in things
that are not good for the mind. uh you
would know if things are if your actions
are rooted in that if you basically
start seeing uh what is the motivation
behind your any action you're doing
you know behind things you want to say
actions you want to perform things you
allow your mind to think all of that has
to be rooted in something in some desire
or the other and that's what you want to
start to pay attention Yeah.
So when the the feeling of panic comes
and you have this
um
horrible feeling you can't stay um put
you can't sit. You have to get up and
walk and think about
the the thoughts that you have is like
oh I how could I do this? what happened?
Um, oh, I'm going to fix this and and you
oh, I'm going to fix this and and you
can't stop your mind going into fire.
What do you do in that in that?
Well, you see that that condition is is
not the problem. That's the result of
the problem.
So, when the panic comes on that level,
that's the result of everything else
before. Or when the panic wasn't there,
you haven't kept your mind in check.
when things were good, when things were
not, when things were going your way,
you haven't kept your mind in check and
you should have done the same. So now
when things have changed, that mind that
you haven't kept in check overwhelms
you.
So at that point, you make sure you
don't do anything on account of that
panic until the panic goes away.
And then when the
when the panic goes away, that's when
you do the work. Okay? So now I'll be
careful not just in regard to panic and
other things but in regard to things
that I deem to be good and acceptable
and I have right to and so on.
So like again mind is a wild animal. I
say that often or how wild it is is how
wild you let it be. So if you let that
animal roam around when it wants, it's
only going to be relatively tamed. So
when something upsets it, when
circumstances pressure it, it will turn
against you because that's what a wild
dog would do. It has no respect and it
certainly does not see you as somebody
who is in charge because you never made
yourself in charge of your own mind, not
of the circumstances around you.
So So that's what you do. Start taming
it. How?
How?
Yeah. As I said, be aware of your
motivation behind your actions. Even
when the actions are good, that doesn't
mean you should be ignorant of the
reasons for you doing it. Be mindful of
your behavior. Don't do anything on
account of greed, aversion, ill will,
malice. Even if it feels right to say something,
Even if it feels right to say something,
if it's rooted in unh wholesome in your
mind, you don't do it.
So, you don't use the external world for
the criteria what should be done. you
use your state of mind as a criteria for
what should be done. Um so it's going to
take time to develop that but again the
problems you're having are not problems
that were created overnight either. So
in the same sense it's going to take
time to to
un unwind them. Yeah. Okay.
Yeah. Okay.
A lot of work to do.
Well, yeah. But see, at least
recognizing that this is work to be
done, that's a good first step. Many
people just refuse to accept even that.
No, they still just want the pill to
manage the symptoms. And for that, you
don't really need Buddhist teaching.
Any distraction is already a form of
pill, which is why the condition gets
worse because you just keep managing the
headache of it.
So if you're if you're constantly
monitoring your intentions,
uh your motivation, what drives your
actions, your speech, your everything,
um then when panic hits or you know,
then you're pretty sure that you've done
everything right. Right. Because you
have you would at least be less doubtful
you would at least be less doubtful
about it. Exactly.
Yeah. Yeah. And that's that's the that's the
Yeah. And that's that's the that's the
aggregate of virtue and the proper
behavior that if you actually develop
beforehand, you don't see the benefit at
a time necessarily. There is no
immediate, you know, great reward and
permanent perpetual sunshine because
you're virtuous. But yes, when the mind
goes into those states, you realize
you're not as moved as much. And now you
know why?
Because your behavior has been kept in
check and purified beforehand.
And also if you keep an eye on these
things you will re-evaluate uh even
things that you think are important to
you now
which on account of which you suffer
basically when you you know separated
from things you want united with things
you don't want it's the basis of
suffering. So you will reevaluate what you want and
So you will reevaluate what you want and
what you don't want as well
and you know where you should be and
what a good life is. You know, most of
those things people don't really sit
down and think about, you know, in in
great depth. They just assume it, take
it at a face value, then add a new face
value to it, then go through life with
it, then add a new face value and just
keep kind of piling on of these random
values that if you stop and think about
it, you realize I don't really even care
about these things or not as much as I
thought I did.
I think you were just speaking about
similar things with uh uh with another
monk that the video was just published
on YouTube and I was listening listening
to half of it. It was about emotions,
how to deal with and I thought it was
really helpful. Um, and uh, one thing
that you said kind of stuck with me and
you said that the emotions are there,
but they're not mine,
per se. They're it's not something, you
know, that I have
um that
Yeah. You're subjected to them. Yeah.
And they become yours when you act out
of them. When you take them for granted,
when you can't help yourself, and you
act either for prolonging the good ones
or getting rid of the bad ones. They're
basically a bait that hooks you.
But if you if if again if you keep your
behavior in check, your speech, your
mind, a tedious process in the
beginning, I know you are creating a
container. Now, they will they will
prevent you pretty much from jumping
into that gratuitous ownership of what
feelings arose in you that you had no
say in. But you can't just choose when
the feeling is there to say, I don't own
this because you know it's not a matter
of choice.
It's a result of prior development
or a lack of it.
Yeah. I find this very helpful when
panic strikes to be in that in the body
in to observe what's happening to be
living through what's happening.
Well, see that's there's another thing
now that you said that the panic strikes
Why? Yeah.
Yeah.
Why is there a need? No, no, no. Why is
there a need to get rid of the panic
when it comes? Why is there an automatic
need to not have this?
This is so this is probably something
very innate to all human beings. We want
to get rid of it.
Well, see now, how do you know that?
Have you investigated every human being
and and arrived at a conclusion?
No. But
from your point of view,
the attitude of not accepting panic
immediately want to get rid of it, which
is what incidentally makes the panic
worse. Yeah.
Yeah.
Why is that? So what innate human
ability to make its own panic worse?
That doesn't sound like an evolution.
That's strange.
So you [clears throat] have to you first
want to react. You want to you want to
call somebody. You want to write that
email. you wanted to do that first do
something then you
because you want to get rid of the pain
behind it because it's very unpleasant
it's very unpleasant and then you you
can develop ticks you can there there
are all sorts of things but then when
you kind of
that's what I'm saying panic is like an
extreme scenario of your day-to-day life
if you have not been cultivating mind
that wants to get rid of discomfort
whenever it arises that would not have
been your first protocol when panic
manifests It's a habit that you're
cultivating. So that's why I said endure
the panic until it subsides and then
keep an eye basically on what you do
because that's the root of the problem.
And if you stop habitually just try to
get rid of discomfort and not think
about it and so on or prolong the
pleasure and not think about it, you are
creating more and more space for you to
hold that panic without being without
panicking.
Because panic is not measured by how
much panic you feel. Panic is measured
by how much of that panic moves you
around.
And that was the whole point of that
emotions talk. It's not about not having
emotions of good or bad kind. It's about
being moved by them and acting out of
them. That's how you measure the
problem, not by what you felt. uh perhaps
uh perhaps
break down a given phenomenon say either
pain or anxiety whichever you prefer.
Uhhuh. So that we do it a bit more
So that we do it a bit more
analytically.
Um
here's a first attempt. So uh there is a
certain quality say of a feeling which manifests
quality say of a feeling which manifests
itself in a specific way. You know what
is pain, you know what is anxiety and so
on and so forth. Right?
But we often conflate this specific
quality also with our tendency to
respond to that particular quality. So
we see we we we have a certain emotive
texture and immediately because things
happen so quickly we tend to think well
anxiety and then everything that follows
this is part of it but this is precisely
not the case not the point right the
point is that there is
but also hold on before we go too far
it's also
yes um it's not quite the way you describe
um it's not quite the way you describe
it because
well whether it's anxiety whether it's
panic whether it's any of those states
You list what do they all have in
common? They are felt unpleasantly
and they remain to be felt unpleasantly
throughout your experience of them. So it's not
your experience of them. So it's not
that first moment that you made a
mistake and acted out of it. See if a
panic halfway through panic ceases to be
painful, it will cease to be panic.
Yes. And you would not have to stop yourself
And you would not have to stop yourself
from acting and fixing it because you
don't feel the panic anymore.
Which means it's not a momentary
reaction. It's more like you are under
the pressure of that same discomfort
throughout. For as if the panic lasts
for hours, it's the same discomfort.
Yes. Okay. I agree with that. So I mean
at that at that level you must endure
it. Not like oh if I didn't act back
then or next time I won't act in the
beginning. Doesn't matter.
I understand
for the duration of the discomfort you
should remain basically aware of it and
not act out of it.
Okay. Yes, I understand it. So maybe I
phrased it awkwardly or wrongly in the
sense of that it sounded as if it was a
you know a point in time. I just meant
it could be even spread out temporally
as you described. There is a certain
quality of unpleasantness that is there
or quality of painfulness maybe.
Yeah. Yeah.
Uh
so so but then there is this other
segment of
what would we call it? what we call it.
So that there is a quality of
painfulness or anxiety or what have you.
And then there's this responsive element
of me trying to push or get rid of this,
right? Like this re reactive segment
that we often conflate. We think that
this like Martina said, but this is how
we respond. But to a certain degree
that's true, but but also you you see
that there's a segment there where
Yeah. That segment is what you're
responsible for. Yeah.
Okay. That's not to say, as I said, it's a
That's not to say, as I said, it's a
matter of conscious choice. You can just
stop it but it is your doing
either has been accumulated over a
period of time of not keeping yourself
in check. So if you unaccumulate it, it
will cease. That response will cease.
Uh but yes it is. Yes, that that whole
automatic response of I don't want this.
That's not part of the feeling. That's
not part of the panic either.
But would you say that uh s say um
um
a capable or a well-developed disciple
does he or she still
experience panic? Pain definitely for sure. Yeah,
panic? Pain definitely for sure. Yeah,
it experience some sort of discomfort.
But you wouldn't use the same word panic
that you use for somebody who is not
experienced and developed disciple
because as I said panic is when you are
panicked when you took the ownership of
it. You're moved by it. You're acting
out of it. You're trying to get rid of
the discomfort blindly. If you don't do
those things, that panic will cease to
be making you panic.
Mhm. So you could say that overall phenomena
So you could say that overall phenomena
that discomfort, that uncomfortable
experience is still there. The threat is
there, the risk is there, but the
pressure behind it that was making you
lose perspective, that's not there. Cuz
now your perspective is greater. Yeah,
I understand because that in in a
certain sense what we were now
describing analytically
what we call panic after all is the
whole phenomena. It is you that that
basically in a certain sense create
panic. there is the element of
unpleasantness the quality there is and
and this will remain for instance if I
understand correctly this is also this
has also been my experience through the
years of for example
no exactly that's why the most practical
thing you can do is stop thinking you
must get rid of it stop thinking I must
prevent this from even arising because
it's so unpleasant no and nobody can
avoid that one way or the other it comes
anxiety unless the mind is enlightened
So your duty is not to not experience
it, to prevent it from arising, to make
it go away as quickly as possible. Your
duty is to not be moved by it for as
long as it lasts. That's it. And
incidentally, that will make it go away,
but not on your own terms.
And it's that that inability to give up
that my own [snorts] terms. That's why
you're still subjected to it.
There's a corlary question to this. This
is something that it's become more in
interesting or important for me now.
Would you agree that there's also an
interesting story to be story to be said
about this particular quality? So we
talked about panic itself when it
manifests itself in the acute manner
sense that Mariana and Martino were
talking about and but there's this also
this quality and would you say that this
particular quality quality of
unpleasantness is something that arises
against the background of conditions
which are related to you living an unh
wholesome life. This was my experience
that if I as you said uh
proceed to to to try to the best of my
ability to uh realize and manifest the
the the qualities
the wholesome qualities
then the
the the frequency or yeah the frequency
of these the the the the unpleasant
quality manifesting itself diminish. is
greatly or completely disappears as long
as I am somehow capable of maintaining
this then this becomes
significantly reduced I wouldn't say
that completely
so so this is something that I think is
also important uh so that there are
there's this uh one way of coping with
panic that we've described but then also
what do you do with the quality so how
do you reduce the the the negative qu
the the the frequency of this negative
quality appearing in
but you don't why would you want to
reduce that if it doesn't bother you in
the f first place anymore
because that you still are able to
differentiate between this particular
quality and the quality say of
well-being which is
right right but no if if the obviously
if you are not causing the panic
yourself and the panic manifests it's not you're
and the panic manifests it's not you're
doing
so you trying to manage that
preemptively means you still know you're not free
means you still know you're not free
from the pressure of it. That's why you
still value if the thing doesn't even
arise. No, you need to be completely
indifferent towards manifestation of
panic. And by that I mean you need to be
And by that I mean you need to be
completely unmoved by it. So that's
where I disagree. Your virtuous behavior
and wholesome life does not reduce the
frequency necessarily. You know maybe
some actions, maybe the environment you
live in that's contributing to frequency
and so on. What that does reduce your
wholesome behavior is the extent of
oscillation of your mind on account of
it. Before it would swing from one wall to
Before it would swing from one wall to
the other. Now it barely kind of
shutters a little bit and then it goes
away and it doesn't care. It doesn't
move. Not that the problem is not there.
It's just you are now able to not act
out of that irrational pressure which
when you act out of makes the pressure
worse. In the same sense, you know, like
when you're kids and you're afraid of
the dark, the fear doesn't overwhelm you
until you choose to start running.
That's when you really get scared. When
you start running, but if you don't
start running, the pressure is there,
but it doesn't overwhelm you. But if you
don't want even that pressure to be
there, that's when the fear enters you.
And there is a fear and dread sa the
Buddha is describing exactly the same.
He would go to the places basically
where no people go, only wild beasts.
and he's walking doing walking
meditation at night and there will be a
sound or something nearby his mind will
think ah here is that dangerous deadly
thing coming your way now and he said I
wouldn't change my position in other
words he wouldn't stop walking until he
first dispels that urgency to act out of
that fear
because if he acts out of that fear if
he sits down or hides or something well
he just gave into the fear obviously
that's what he was describing I mean on
a much subtler level but it's the same
principle. You are not afraid by feeling
pressure. You're not panicked by feeling
that pressure of anxiety. You're panic
by acting out of it and trying to outrun
it. So how much you move by it, that's the
So how much you move by it, that's the
problem, not what has manifested for
you. Okay. The way that you now put it, it
Okay. The way that you now put it, it
might be the case that because of the
virtuous background makes your
confrontation with the quality less
problematic. the quality itself ends up.
So yeah, yeah,
and that's why often you have in the
sutras like for inance problem still
kept coming and the Buddha would say,
"Oh, it's because of the previous karma
or something." The qualities would still
keep coming for whatever reason for
stuff they did or said, but no pressure
would be there for them and the mind
wouldn't move either way.
But it's not that they never experience
problem on that factual level in terms
of, you know, discomfort or issues and
so on.
So that's what I'm saying. Even even if
it's the extreme panic, the point is you
recognize, okay,
it's not supposed to not be here.
It's not supposed to not be felt like
this. The only thing I'm not supposed to
do is keep perpetuating it through my
rational actions on account of it. So as
bad as it is, let me wait it out.
Literally, not ignore it.
just wait for it to subside and then if
I still want to do the same thing I
wanted to do when I was all panicked
I'll do it but it won't be rooted in
panic but if I keep doing it in panic it keeps
but if I keep doing it in panic it keeps
adding to the panic
and that's the painful development there
that you have to endure it because it
feels like well if I just start running
the danger will be left behind but No,
it won't. Because now the danger enter
you through that fear that you created
through your running.
And you would start running when you
feel when you have a view or have a
degree of entitlement that you shouldn't
be feeling that pressure in the first
place. And that's not up to you to
decide. That's up to the elements, the
aggregates, and the circumstances.
It's whether you act out of it or not.
That's up to you.
So even when people want to manage
panic, that's fine. But don't manage it
by trying to not have it or prevent it
or get rid of it, manage it by keeping
yourself in control while it's there.
Manage it by learning how to endure it.
Manage it by removing the view that
makes you think you shouldn't feel it in
the first place
because that's completely not true.
I would have a different question if
nobody has anything else. But uh
uh
in the traditional setting
um
the notion or the idea related to um
later births that could happen in
different realms of being or existence.
provided in a certain sense a framework
that would allow someone for example a
lay person or or a disciple who felt
that maybe
he is not progressing as much as he
could have a certain hope or a certain
solace that I don't know maybe he will
be born in in a in a realm that is
beneficial in one of the realms of the
god but
Someone in in who has grown up in the
contemporary western society usually has
severe difficulties accepting this this
story this narrative this context. So
for that person it's almost like being
or walking on the razor's edge
which in a certain sense is good this
thing of some of existential you know
you either fall on the one side or you
fall on the other side or whatever. So
you know damnation there, damnation
there and enlightenment on the razor's
edge. But would you say what would your
But would you say what would your
approach be to this? Would you try to
somehow for example help the
someone in the west to enter into this
framework, the traditional Buddhist
framework of different realms of beings
and existence of of gods and demons? And
if you would, how would you do this? How
would you bring these phenomena closer
to someone or would you insist
ra or would you rather have that person
have this feeling of walking on the
razor's edge uh and just you know
well no I don't think I would I would
bring it to them because it would be
quite it wouldn't be practical really it
would be just making them adopt one set
of external belief on account of another
one so the most you can do is make Sure that
so the most you can do is make Sure that
they are aware of the like
responsibility behind their actions and
the result that they can see in this
life and then say if you behave in this
way you will benefit in this life. See
you know if you practice sense restraint
you will develop patience you will
develop tolerance your mind will not
move in the face of panic. Great things
everybody values those things. So you
win in this life on account of being
virtuous, keeping the precepts,
practicing mindfulness. Plus the same
teacher who gave these instructions that
you can verify here and now said if you
practice these instructions here and
now, you'll get a future reward as well,
but you don't have to worry about that.
So it's a win-win either way.
[laughter] It's a bit of a Pascal there, right?
It's a bit of a Pascal there, right?
Well, no, no, no. I just actually did a
video on that. I haven't posted it yet.
Pascal didn't see the benefit. Pascal
referred to it as finite loss.
But what why is sense restraint a loss
when you gain from it even here? Pascal
thought that refraining from sensuality
is a factual loss for which you might be
rewarded later. But the Buddha said
refraining from sensuality is a factual
gain from which you might be rewarded
later. So it's the opposite of Pascal's
wager. Do you see the difference there?
Do you see the difference there?
Yeah. Yeah. I see the difference
because people often struggle. Yeah. But
see, you know, why should I forsake my
sense desires here? I don't see the
benefit for the sake of forsaking them.
Do you think you develop patience by
scratching an itch like a wild animal or
by refraining from scratching the itch?
Again, common wisdom.
Who has greater chance of success even
in life? person who has a better context
on a kind of refraining from impulsive
action or a person who always acts
impulsively and doesn't care about the
results of their action in this life.
So Pascal was wrong. That's there's no
loss either way. Sense restraint,
virtue, keeping your sense desires in
check. It's a gain either way.
And yeah, if you keep if you Exactly. If
you keep little bit in check, you you
win a little bit. doesn't mean oh so I
must forsake the life and be celibate
for the rest of my life if that's what
you want to do sure and to that extent
you probably have a greater chance of
even bigger peace if you do it but again
in the most mundane terms uh people who
want to succeed in life succeed in
family who is better off the one who has
work ethic who doesn't just follow his
desires who is able to hold back who is
able to contain himself who is able to
have perspective on his situation
despite the pressuring pull of I want
this, I don't want that. Or the one who
is the opposite to that or the one who's
just scratching it and chases after what
what it takes. It's fancy.
So, it's a win-win either way because
those very things you've done in the
next life will reward you if there is
one.
here immediately somebody if we're
already talking on this particular level
somebody might bring up you know someone
like I don't know Elon Musk or Jeff
Bezos or whatnot and they are not
particularly virtuous people they are
hyper you know millilar they're
billionaires and uh uh extremely
influential uh they seem to be enjoying
their life in many different ways and
somebody might say why would I want to
you know forsake with these things. Why
would I not want to scratch the itch if
if scratching the itch might allow me to
be the person who and I'm playing the
devil's? Yeah. Yeah, I know. Well, because Ela
Yeah. Yeah, I know. Well, because Ela
Musk and Jeff Basus or whoever got there
by not scratching their edge. They got
there by working, by not giving into the
immediate desire and having a bigger
picture of a greater reward later.
They got there because they were sensed
for one reason or the other.
So yeah, that's the argument that you
gave yourself as a devil's advocate.
That's why you shouldn't do it because
those very people didn't do it.
But they lack wisdom. Is that
Yeah, sure. We're not talking about
wisdom now. We're talking about how much
you allow yourself to go down the
pathway of sensual desire and acting out
of an impulse which is often always
basically kind of the the point that
people come to when they speak about the
next life. Well, why should I be
virtuous? Why should I say no to these
things? This is why because you'll
benefit in this life on account of it.
But people even the as I said the most
mundane people you just listed I'm sure
they do recognize what has resulted or
or what has brought those results for
them. They know that it wasn't you know
staying late at night and partying with
the fratmates and so on. It was the
opposite. And how many people are able
to do the opposite? Well, not many.
That's why not many are billionaires
because it's hard to it's hard to
restrain at that point and keep this far
removed distant picture that it's still 50/50 at
distant picture that it's still 50/50 at
best in mind as your goal. No, just give
me something immediately now. That's
what I want. And that's exactly why why
you're basically subjected then to the
same desires on and on and on and on. Gone. Sorry.
Gone. Sorry.
Yeah, I just kind of reminded me of
something that um I was discussing with
my friend the other day. It was uh we
were discussing how you know how we tend
to um compare ourselves to others whom
we see as more successful, more more
[snorts] beautiful, more influential.
But what we don't know is the way they
are experiencing themselves.
Well, exactly. No, I just I just took
the argument at a face value and even in
that case I wanted to say that even they
are you know they might not see the
value of what what they how they went
about it but again if somebody does make
the effort and practice sense restraint
they will benefit in this life through
developing mental states they will be
more conducive to their own peace but
yes what you're saying now is exactly
the point somebody might be a
millionaire but that's not a measure
of his success internally at all.
Like you could imagine yourself being a
millionaire that's extremely miserable.
And why would you take like what would
be better for you to not be a
millionaire and be very contented and
happy or to be a millionaire and be
absolutely like a wreck? Everybody
already you know what you would choose.
So that's the whole point here. But um
yeah, mental states will determine
basically your happiness and uh and
that's another thing that you can you
can recognize in the most mundane
setting. What results in better calming,
more contented, more um self-sufficient
mental states? Is it chasing after
desires like a wild dog or actually
being able to hold back and you know
control myself, keep myself in check
because otherwise I'm going to enter a
rabbit hole and I won't be able to leave
for a while and it's going to be very
unpleasant like it has been so many
times before.
So in the most mundane basic wisdom non
Buddhist practice, anybody can see this
for themselves. It's still beneficial.
What are some of the exercises that you
can do or how can you train your mind
like daily every day that you do you do
that? Well, you can familiarize yourself with
Well, you can familiarize yourself with
the precepts, five precepts, eight
precepts in in Buddhism, which is
basically the like modes of behavior,
things to not do and be mindful of.
Um, and that's pretty much the context
of your exercises. Then everything else
that they throws at you, it's seen
against those or is this according to
the precepts or against the precepts and
there is no budging there. You don't
compromise the framework of the precept
because by developing your behavior in
that sense, setting boundaries and the
correct framework, then your speech will
follow and then you'll be able to do the
same to your mind. But you can't bypass
body speech and then just affect the
mind which is where the problem is. Yes.
But in order to arrive with it, to be
able to deal with it, you need to take
it up from the roots
and then eventually you come to the the
mind, right? This is where the pen the
problem is. And I like what you just
said just wrote it down in chat. So you
said your mind will not move in the face
of panic. So you didn't say you will not
experience panic.
No. No. Exactly.
I like that. Yes.
Well, that's important because people
think I must not be experiencing this.
Mhm. And that's why you're experiencing it.
And that's why you're experiencing it.
Yeah.
Oh, this fire shouldn't be here. So you
stick your hands and try to get rid of
the fire. And that's why that fire is a
problem for you. [clears throat] If you
stop touching it, it will stop burning
you and it will burn itself out and
there was no problem. The problem was
you jumping into it trying to get rid of
it. But you can't, as I said, just
decide to not jump into it because
that's your mode of behavior throughout
the day. Discomfort, jump into it to get
rid of it. Comfort, jump into it to
prolong it.
So the precepts are the the framework
and that's where your mindfulness and
composure comes from. And none of the
experiences should change in that sense.
It's [clears throat] how much you moved
on account of it that's that's what will
change. Yeah. So it's it's exactly the same
Yeah. So it's it's exactly the same
thing with desires. Of course we see
something that we like we this because
you have this somehow ingrained in your
mind. If it feels good I should be able
to do it right. I should allow myself to
do it because it feels good. It's good
for me.
It's not really good for you in the long
run. And again, you won't be able to not
allow yourself just everything overnight
or something. But the point is to not
lose the sight of your responsibility
for allowing yourself.
Oh, it feels good. So, I should do it.
Thus, I will be responsible for doing
it. Okay. So, shall I do it? Well, maybe
let me reconsider because now I feel the
weight of those actions on me.
And then sometimes when you do it,
you'll do it responsibly. When you don't
do it, you will be equally responsible
and aware of it.
But it's when people act out of their
view, which is pretty much like a sense
of entitlement. Oh, it's fine. Like, why
would I, you know, there's no problem
with this and it's not my fault that I'm
feeling it. And it's not my fault that
I'm acting out of it.
And I'm not responsible for it. It's
just acting, reacting, and so on.
And that view has to change. So you're
not responsible for panic or for
pleasure coming your way, but you're
certainly responsible what you do on
account of it.
Beings are owners of their actions.
Beings are not owners of the, you know,
feelings and panics and anxieties and
pleasures that come their way, but
they're owners of what they do on
account of it.
Wonderful. I think you have wrapped it
up really nicely. I'm not sure if
there's any follow-up questions.
Maybe one that is related to this um
actions and intentions.
Uhhuh. So it would seem that uh
the notion of kama in Buddhism is
related not to say the specific concrete
actions that you perform but the the
behavioral intentions that you so the
the way you polarize yourself towards a
certain something. So the attitude
itself is in a certain sense the the
rudimentary and crucial uh aspect in
this right.
Yeah that's what Buddha said every
action is intention.
Okay. Yeah. So could you maybe just
slightly elaborate on this? So how how
what the what exactly does this mean and
how how you perceive of it? Why why it
might be significant? I mean there are
certain things that I already kind of
you know took from this but I would just
like to
well basically it means that your
intention behind the actions determines
whether that action is wholesome or not.
Sure, some obvious actions are unh
wholesome and cannot be done with a
wholesome intention, you know, such as
killing, stealing, lying, cheating, and
so on. You can't do that for good.
Doesn't matter what you tell yourself.
It has to be rooted in that individual
unh wholesome intention. But certain
like if if it's not those extreme
things, uh most of the other actions are
determined basically by your intention.
So as I gave many similars before like
you know you could say well going to a
monastery is a good thing not by itself
it's good if your intention to go to a
monastery is rooted in good
good reason good purpose not for
something unh wholesome but if it is
then it's not good so if you go to the
monastery to basically I don't know
learn the dharma yeah that's good
because that can bring further wisdom
and so But if you go to monastery to you
know socialize, steal, spend time,
whatever else, it's the same action
externally. We're talking about going to
the monastery. But that's not what
determines whether it's good or bad. But
people do like to think do like to take
the letter of the action, so to speak,
as the measure of if it's good or not.
No, it's it's it's good to go to the
monastery. It's good to do this. Well, as I said in
It's good to do this. Well, as I said in
those obvious examples, certain things,
yes, are always good and and certain
things are not good. But all of this is
determined by the intention behind the
action of doing them. So why do you want
to go to monastery?
And if you know that with yourself,
you're getting to know the roots of your
own actions. But if you just take the
face value of going to the monastery is
always good. That's it. There's no work
for you.
You just cover it up. There's nothing
else that exists there. Just doing good
means this is good. Let me not think
about the reasons why I'm doing it.
And incidentally, that's also why I
would not try to change the westerners's
mind about you know believing in heavens
and rebirths and different realms
because it would be on that level.
Okay, I adopt this idea and do this and
that's it. I don't need to be
self-aware. No, you do need to be
self-aware because fundamentally the
idea I gave you, how do you know it's
right? You don't. But what you do know
is the reasons for your actions on a
day-to-day basis. You know exactly where
they're rooted. Is this in desire? Is
this aversion? Is this distraction
delusion? Is this non-desire,
non-version, non-distraction, non-d
delusion? Will this bring more
self-awareness as a result? Or will this
bring the self-awareness to diminish as
a result?
what am I what I'm about to do?
So that's why some people just use this
very instruction and became when the
Buddha said just whatever you know it's
unh wholesome abandon it as in rooted in
unh wholesome don't do it and root in
wholesome do it whatever you know that
will bring the increase of unh wholesome
and decrease of wholesome don't do it
and opposite if it increases wholesome
and decreases unh wholesome do it
but can you fully understand the
phenomenon of intention and uh comma
without presupposing
past and future birth. So that the
reason why I'm asking this is whether
you know because you said one of the
reasons why you wouldn't want to go
well there is no there is what you mean
by fully understanding the phenomenon of
kama. What I mean by that is I mean in the
What I mean by that is I mean in the
sense of uh can you really understand
the gravitas or the the the weight of of
the past conditions?
No no only relatively nobody can only
the Buddha could understand that. And he
himself said trying to think about the
weights the the workings of the kama and
how it happened and the results that are
waiting will only bring madness and
distraction. No, but you can directly see for
No, but you can directly see for
yourself that by not giving into the unh
wholesome kinds of intention behind your
action, your mind will move less and
less in regard to things that move you that
in regard to things that move you that
are always felt unpleasantly.
So you will have a dharma verifiable
here and now that result in un
unmovability and pretty much uh inability to suffer
and pretty much uh inability to suffer
on account of things they used to make
you suffer
and you don't need a you can't even get
any theory any theoretical answer any
magical display of workings of kama
cannot be as direct as this proof that
dhamma is working well where you can't
suffer amidst that which make you suffer
because of your practice and restraint
and mind field purification developed
beforehand. [snorts]
Okay. So basically
visible here and now. Okay.
Okay.
I guess uh
yeah that's that's probably a good point
and it probably circumvents all the you
know Yeah. Everything else is second to it.
Yeah. Everything else is second to it.
Exactly. Yeah.
Yeah. The prototypical objections of, you
The prototypical objections of, you
know, you have bad people and then
they're prosperous and mantra.
Yeah. So, yeah. Yeah.
So, yeah. Yeah.
Prosperity does not mean happiness.
Mhm. I've I've seen you walk uh the
hills. I've seen you walk mountains. Um
you seem to be very outdoorsy kind of
very active uh person. And uh I was just
wondering uh while you do while you're
on your hikes, on your walks, uh
how do you what do you what do you do?
Do you are you mindful of your
body during that? You know, do you do
you kind of make a practice out of it or
um No, I tend to walk fast. So basically
the breathing becomes very hard and you
feel like you're dying and then the mind
doesn't move in face of that.
So that's my hiking practice and
tracking practice.
Basically expose yourself to the
elements so the mind doesn't move in
those extreme circumstances.
Yeah, we do a bit of um sports
ourselves, but yeah. So,
um I I was wondering how Yeah. what what
kind of things to incorporate while you
know when when you're on a longer bike
ride, it gets pretty boring or so. So,
it's it's a nice time.
Yeah. I'm not I'm not doing it like for
for for in that sense like for some
pleasure or something like especially in
Sri Lanka when I used to go around the
jungles on my own. The whole point was
go through the difficult terrains that I
know I cannot turn back and go back to
the comfort. Once you cross that point,
it would be harder to turn back than to
keep going forward. And then you just
have to endure it until it ends without
your mind. Well, see that's it. The mind
wants to panic. The mind wants to move.
The mind wants to change. The mind wants
to deal with the circumstances. But you
don't. You just endure it physically. So
that's that purification that what I was
talking about it to during the elements
and during discomfort.
It's not some great practice that you
kind of need to predetermine. You just
need to expose yourself to to it and see
how much your mind moves. Obviously I
remember in the beginning it was moving
much more. Just the thought of doing
that was moving me
years ago.
And and you see that like the thought of
discomfort, physical rain, cold, you
know, being stuck in the jungle in the
vines and everything, leeches. Oh, you
know, I can't be bothered.
And again, you don't do it blindly. Oh,
that's why I'll just do it. No, do it so
to be bothered so to not be moved by the
physical body. Because what do you
think? How will the illness feel when
the body starts breaking apart?
Joint aching, head hurting, eyes cannot
see, you can barely breathe. It's going
to feel exactly like that.
Yeah. And that's why first thing you get
And that's why first thing you get
people who are hiking is they become
very grumpy. [laughter]
They start arguing with each other as
well because they start lashing out
because it starts building up just basic
discomfort and most people are sheltered from it.
and most people are sheltered from it.
[snorts]
So that's why I do it so you don't
become complacent. Sorry.
It's wonderful because I'm always trying
to avoid the discomfort, right? I don't
want to go on that bike ride. I know
it's going to take very long time. It's
going to be very dangerous. It's going
to be uphill and whatever. Um but then
when I do it, I really enjoy that
feeling. Exactly what you're describing
when I
You can Yeah, you can you can avoid the
danger part. There's no need to be like
life-threatening or something. But yeah,
you you do that endurance and uh
Exactly. Yeah. Once the mind stops
moving in the face of that, it's not
going to move into anything that's
inferior to that.
Great. So I can incorporate Dharma into
many things. So I do not need that time
slot after all.
Yeah, exactly. Yeah. Yeah. [laughter]
Sorry, did you have a question as well?
Yeah. Yeah,
we have a question here as well.
Yeah. Um, so um just just to check if I
understand you correctly with this not
wanting to have um panic and and other
stuff. So it seems to me that um um on
the on the one level it seems to me that
it is sort of understandable that I
don't want them because I don't want
them uh because I want to be sort of
enlightened. Um, so I I'd say
um so um so not not wanting so so to say
perceiving them as a problem maybe not
so bad so to say because um
because this makes you aware that you
are not enlightened now and um
um
yeah and and this also can Then a way to
to say to to soothe sooth this
discomfort, s this this um uh desire to
to get rid of them because once you
remind yourself that it is also normal
that you experience this these feelings
um because you're not enlightened. This
is already sort of um well brings brings
them down because you you don't perceive
them anymore as something as something
which is which should not be there. It
should be there just because you're not
I see what you mean but no no they
they're not a problem.
No. Uh see you saying that they are the
problem means saying they are the
suffering but suffering is not in the
phenomena. It's not in dharmas. It's not
in the things. It's in your craving in
regard to them. That's the first noble
truth. So, ironically enough, yes,
enlightenment will make those things not
be there. Not because they are not
there. It's because you have no craving
in regard to them.
Because the noble truth of craving is
not there is no panic attack
manifesting. There is no discomfort
manifesting. The noble truth of craving is there is
The noble truth of craving is there is
no resistance and discomfort left
whatsoever ever again.
So the root of suffering is tanha, not
the world. things remain standing in the
world coming you I mean I'm sure angula
when after his arahanship when those
kids threw stones and split his head
open I'm sure he felt the discomfort on
account of it otherwise the Buddha
wouldn't have come to him and said bury
it brahin bur it otherwise the results
you know if you didn't become an arahan
would have been far worse than what
you're experiencing now
but he had no craving left so that's why
it's I know what you mean like yeah
because you could then just say okay so
let's not make a problem out of anything
and forget that you're not enlightened.
But I think people that are gripped by
panic attacks, they don't need reminders
that they're not enlightened. They know
that very well and they feel it. They
need a reminder to see where the line of
the problem is. And panic is not that.
Your resistance to it is which is there
because of your equal non-resistance to
pleasure when it's there beforehand or
after. Yeah. Yeah.
Go follow.
Yeah. So another thing so let's say in
in the in the working context so many of
us find ourselves in well in the
situations where so non-acting is so to
say dangerous
to career. So and for me it basically
means that you need to to give up those
to to leave those contexts.
Sure. Yeah. Well, that's yeah, that's
the conflict that you in your setting
need to resolve with yourself.
Practice of dharma. Yeah. You cannot be
working and being a layman and
fulfilling the practice of dharma. You
can only do in a limited manner
because Yeah. It is mutually exclusive.
Exactly. Because the more you do it, the
more you will be sort of withdrawing
yourself from all the other things you
need to do. So you can't have it both
ways. Yeah. And so maybe last question on my
Yeah. And so maybe last question on my
side. So um I after I started doing um
well I could well maybe one could call
like this practice of nonactivity just I
don't know to sit down and I don't know
to to sit for let's say maybe an hour
minute two hours to see how the mind
comes down in it. I found it very
very pleasant. Uh and and I said myself
as I started asking myself um so is this
pleasure now a problem that I'm sort of
enjoying basically like this stuff maybe
I don't know uh how much of it is maybe
essential pleasure because I sort of
allow my body to rest. Yeah. So my
question is is it is it a problem that
that you're experiencing pleasure on
account of your
well what kind of pleasure like
contentment mental joy
yeah some stuff like this yeah so you're
just the the the I mean the feeling that
that you're
do you become unaware of yourself on
account of that pleasure do you become
distracted do you feel like you woke up
when that pleasure ceases or you remain
fully mindful while the pleasure is
Yeah. Um well um I think I remain mindful of
Um well um I think I remain mindful of
it. Yeah. So it's a
Yeah. So keep an eye for as long as you
remain mindful and it's clearly the
result of you not engaging with your
senses, it's not the pleasure you should
be overly concerned with.
Yeah. But I'm asking myself, so maybe
it's like maybe it's because I'm sitting
in a chair and this is pleasant. So
sure it might be, but that's not the
sensual pleasure. That's not the
pleasure that's inducive of lust,
thirst, and loss of perspective.
But that is certainly the mind of doubt
that's wanting you, wanting to sort of,
you know, move you away from that
experience of non-activity. Want it
wants to make you act.
Hey, stop doing this because it actually
works against the mara's order.
Start thinking about it. Start worrying.
Start undermining it with your yeah mind
comes up with the thought is this. You
check it. Mindfulness is there. you are
not actually engaging with anything.
Yeah. The body feels agreeable. I mean
the Buddha ate the milk rice
and indeed those aesthetics thought look
he he went back he lost it.
He was just the atmos sensuality.
So to some extent yeah you must not
torture the body all the time. Mhm.
But equally what I was talking about
this hiking thing, it's like most people
would not be asking that question to
themselves what you're asking. They
would probably be on the level of I
don't want to deal with the discomfort
even of the basic elemental kind unless
I really have to.
Uh and that's then their practice is to
know actually let me see how much will
my mind move on account of things that
are not threatening to my life. Like you
know I remember leeches in Sri Lanka.
People would lose their mind on account
of it. It's like there's nothing you
can't get diseases from them. They you
know there's no permanent then it's just
unpleasant and psychologically
uncomfortable and and people will just like forsake
and and people will just like forsake
any sense of reason just on account of
those things. It's like you should not
be allowing that yourself like monks if
you want to practice and so on. Uh
because yeah, how do you think it's
going to feel when the body starts
breaking apart in zone when these little
external discomforts are are throwing
you left and right? But yeah, then you
have the other extreme where people can
just go and start torturing for the sake
of like self-inflicting pain because
they don't know where the line is
and that's where the line is.
Find the non-activity if it's agreeable.
Don't lose mindfulness on account of it
and that's it.
You won't be doing it. you will have to
get up and do something at some point.
So, and then when you go back if it
happens the same same doesn't matter.
Okay. Thank you very much.
Yeah. My question was about physical
activity actually
in the sense I mean
I understand everyone um perceives these
things differently but for myself I also
let's say saw it in this sense let's
endurance sports let's say as okay it's
first like I mean first yeah athletes um
body training in a way and the other
aspect was um also exposing the mind to
this uncomfortable
sensation and enduring it
and enduring it
but
how do you say
it's it can definitely
strengthen the mind but I think at some
point or but that's probably um like on
a case to case basis
it can also be a distraction from a
neutral feeling I think so for me it was
um then
that's what I mean like as I said before
the whole point is well that's yeah
that's the practice
is to be able to judge where your
motivation is rooted what I said earlier
half an hour ago
you can't just say ah so physical TV is
always good or oh that's always bad
yeah yeah but being aware of like okay
it's me why are you doing exactly so
halfway through your doing of your
physical activity for strengthening your
body and conditioning your mind you ask
yourself am I still doing it for the
same reasons
and then you realize oh no I'm doing it
because I really want to beat that life
and then you stop it. Now you clearly
know that it's the reasons have changed
because reasons change, intentions
change and that's when you don't follow through
and that's when you don't follow through
with the actions on account because this
is always good. That's what it means
like you take responsibility for your
action. Not like you never do that. It's
like you never lose the sight of why
this is done in the first place.
Yeah. Yeah, but in the sense that like
this neutral feeling is on on the more
subtler level and trying to escape it
through um an excuse of training the
mind might be um tricky.
Well, again, you know, sometimes it can
happen, but if you keep doing it, it
will become apparent
and then you'll see if you're doing it
for that reason.
Mhm. Um but it's it's equal again like
how do you think when when back in the
in the day the Buddhist the monks lived
around India when they would go on foot
carry all their possessions that they
had every time for days just to meet the
every time for days just to meet the
Buddha and talk to him for five minutes
and then wander around. I mean you have
you been in Bihar? I don't know if
you've been to India but it's not a
place you want to wander around now and
I can only imagine back then how it was.
I mean today probably soldiers wouldn't
be able to do that physically without
all the gear and equipment and help yet
that was like a normal life you know the
woman goes on a journey with her two
kids across the entire northern India to
visit her family and you know get
attacked by jackals and so on that was
like a normal thing so people were tough
and uh today how many people can say
they can do oh so again why you want to
do it is what matters but don't ignore
the fact that some extent of it needs to
be done still
because that whole um was it a bas
the whole like set of taints as of us to
be abandoned by enduring heat cold
hunger exposure and so on. [snorts]